<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors | i.am.david.fernandez</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Authors</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <link>/authors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>D. Fernandez</title>
      <link>/authors/d.-fernandez/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/d.-fernandez/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R. A. Jarvis</title>
      <link>/authors/r.-a.-jarvis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/r.-a.-jarvis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A. Price</title>
      <link>/authors/a.-price/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/a.-price/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am an Engineer and I love Engineering. Whether in a professional context dealing with software and electrical systems or at home as an amateur gardener setting up a micro spray system for a vegetable garden, I love the challenge of finding and implementing practical, efficient and effective solutions to real-world problems using systematic techniques coupled with creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a keen interest in the development of systems and technologies that blend mechanical, electrical and electronic systems with software-based computation and the application of computational intelligence to problems in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professionally, my primary interest is Software Engineering, creating software systems that solve real-world problems and improve reliability, robustness and efficiency through automation. Peripherally, I am interested in helping businesses formalise and automate their workflows and secure their information to help ensure processes are efficient, effective, repeatable and reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underneath it all, I simply like making things that solve problems, both my own and those of others. In another time, I perhaps may have been a blacksmith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;My hammer is a keyboard, my anvil a workstation, and my steel is an alloy of ones and zeros.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
